all right everyone we're about to
begin give me a thumbs up if you can
hear me so welcome to another
sense-making wormhole brought to you by
the intellectual Explorers Club I'm your
host Peter Lindbergh and these
sense-making wormholes I invited past
podcast guests of mine to engage in
group conversations their design it's
gonna mute a few people and I view these
experiments in collective intelligence
and the people who are facilitating it
the past guests of my podcast they can
design it however they they want really
and today's session is facilitated by my
dear friend Andrew Taggart Andrew is a
practical philosopher philosophical
consultant and my personal favorite a
critic of total work so I'm just gonna
like take andrew in right now and he's
going to lead us for the rest of the
evening so yeah that being said Andrew
off to you thank you very much Peter and
hi everyone so let's begin by finding
our phones wherever they are and turning
them on to mute or vibrate or employ
mode okay
so in this opening bit I would just like
for us to introduce ourselves in the
following manner
first just give us your first name last
name and second whichever question
you're alive to I'll begin and then I'll
tag Peter we'll go around so that
everyone's had a chance to speak and
then we'll move on to a guided
meditation so my name is andrew the
question on the lie of two is
what is possible to glean from this
particular kind shun rrah that I'm
presently calling a we space meditative
discourse so Peter you're up
my name is Peter the question I'm alive
too is what state of being should I be
in right now to make the most of this
experience and I'll tag Hannah
hello my name is Hannah and the question
I'm alive to is what is this and I will
have to step out early unfortunately
this evening for me but wanted to come
check it out and find out what is this
I will tag read thank you hello my name
is Reid nice wonder question I'm alive
too is what does it mean to be alive
doesn't thing I guess it's a lot more
clarification on that yeah thanks I
tagged Khalil I
my name is Khalil pronounce it perfectly
question of my life too is why does why
do deep existential truths have a kind
of feeling remembered that's something
I've always wondered I'll tag a me
hi I'm Amy might be a little loud being
our name in a coffee shop but my
question I guess how can we be who
hashed it to everyone without knowing
their deep sigh oh and I'll tag
[Music]
you
did you get that Altoid Tara
sorry about that hi I'm Tara my question
would be I agree with Reid I'm curious
to know more about what it means to be
alive to something as well I'm going to
tag sorry it's hard I'm on my phone so
it's kind of hard to see all the people
I will tag Ivan hi my name is Ivan Ivan
and my question that is alive is what
andrew means by psycho technologies of
self-transformation
I'm just very curious about that term
and I'm going to tag Tristan
you
Tristan's iPhone is the is the name that
is she
hi sorry I'm still looking at my audio
what was can you repeat the question yes
so the question is what is that to which
you're alive this evening to which I'm
alive this evening which question are
you alive to this evening things just
yet but I think from what you're saying
just before that that is something quite
I'm quite interested in it as well
they're unlikely technologies and
whatnot I'm only pretty new to this
space so forgive me for my ignorance
that's just fine so find someone to tag
next
okay how do I just try to look it's my
first time using this app sir
maybe Amy already went oh sorry I'll
jump in if you want to facilitate this
you can see yeah no worries my name is
Jake and a question I'm most alive to is
how do psycho technologies relate to
social systems and I will tag Taylor
mm-hmm my name is Taylor mmm
I think the question less alive too is
what has everybody here everybody other
than me tag
Tim out of him
I'm Tim what's most alive to me is the
question of how to understand how with
more fluidity to open up and participate
here together into this exploration
and I'll tag the Ryan's come in hey it's
right here
what's feeling most alive to me right
now is how do our modern set of psycho
technologies fit into the greater
context of history where do they fit in
terms of the psycho technologies that
have come before how have they changed
and what is the potential for the
various psycho technologies as we move
into the future and I'm going to take no
one
hi I'm knowing the question what's the
life to me is that's going to happen
here
and I'll tag Jason
you
I
I'm not sure if I'm being heard
we can hear you Jason uncle Jason why
can I question myself off to me is to
pet compatibility between soccer
technologies how do we tell if there's
compatibility issues between different
ways of interacting that's almost a lot
to me at the moment
thank you Anna Donna I had a tag someone
from here I haven't got a screening or
anything
I booked Khalil I really went with I'll
go again or go here
so yeah I'm Khaleel and I have a
question about psycho technologies is
there a path dependence to how when we
use them be kind of effects they have
and who's left you Lee what are you Lee
hello I'm Yu Lee and the question I've
become most alive too after listening to
these other questions is how is it that
the different people participating in
today's conversation are going to
interpret the same content that we're
all going to be hearing about and and
taking away differently but which
similarities are going to stick around
and I wonder if there's any consistency
to the function that those similarities
are going to play out when they start
getting embedded into the institutions
that each of us play a role in yeah
roughly that's what I'm thinking and
I'll take diff next yes my name is dev
and the question that I am thinking
about is how our philosophical
relationship to time for how our
relationships time and shift can change
so looking forward to hearing what this
conversation is about
I'll tag whoever hasn't gone I have no
idea I just a jungle Italy yeah feel
free to jump in
I don't think nate has gone yet why
don't you go next noon
hi I'm Nate I was I decided a lot with
Tim's question so I wanted to chime in
there and I wanted to say that I think
what I am alive to in this conversation
is whether these psycho technologies are
giving us access to something real that
we didn't have access to before and how
that works in a sort of performative or
uncovering ontology I'll tag whoever's
world hasn't gone after me has anyone
not gone yet
you
I think everyone's okay so can everyone
hear me thumbs up
yeah okay and so two things first of all
this is going to be an experiment an
experiential experiment and therefore
some of the questions that are a little
more theoretical nature may not be
answered during the session therefore if
you have those sorts of questions feel
free to email me and I'm sure that Peter
will include my website and the show
notes or somewhere else
so that's the first thing the second
thing is that we're about to embark on a
short guided meditation and so the first
thing to do would be to turn off your
cameras I'll leave mine on everyone else
can turn off cameras beautiful and also
mute your microphone if you haven't done
so yet okay next you might want to find
a comfortable place if you're in a
seated position that's fine if you feel
called to lie on the floor provided that
it's somewhat energetic that would be
fine too you might want to take off your
glasses since that can be a bit of a
hindrance if you're wearing glasses in
what follows it would be lovely to see
whether you're able to go along with the
meditation and if you can that's
wonderful if however you find that you
can't go along with the meditation that
is that there's some kind of resistance
within you then perhaps your meditation
could be beginning to examine the
resistance what is the resistance where
is it does it have a shape or a size or
tone and and that can be a meditation
during the guided meditation or during
the the next section which is our group
meditative discourse
okay let's begin you may want to keep
your eyes open or you can close them
either is fine you might find that
there's a bit more energy if you have
your eyes closed begin with your head
imagine or visualize or sense or feel
that you're installing energy all the
way through your head from the crown of
the head all the way down to the jaw all
of that will be nothing but energy then
begin to install energy in your neck so
that your neck is just energy entirely
filled with and nothing but energy
do the same for your left arm imagine
the entire left arm is nothing more than
nothing other than nothing less than
energy and therefore it is entirely
filled up with energy from the shoulder
joint all the way down to the tips of
the fingers and then do the same for
your right hand you can feel that your
right arm rather is entirely filled with
energy
now turn to your trunk the long trunk
imagine or sense or visualize or feel
that you're installing energy from your
clavicle all the way down to the bottom
of your trunk that includes your heart
your solar plexus your navel your entire
spine the entire front of the trunk the
entire back of the trunk all this is
energy
then take your genitals and your butt
and all that and see it as entirely
energy and now the right leg take the
right leg all the way from the thigh
down to the foot and install energy
there so that the right leg is nothing
more than nothing less than and nothing
other than energy nothing but pulsing
the vibrating energy
and now do the same thing for your left
leg allow energy to be installed
throughout the course of your left leg
all the way to your foot
so that it is nothing more than less
than or other than energy
you
and now imagine that there is some kind
of brush going up and down your body
such that the brush is moving energy
from the bottom of your feet to the top
or crown of your head and back when you
inhale the energy can be regarded as
going up from the feet through the
middle of the body all the way to the
crown every inhalation the energy flows
as it were upward every exhalation
allows the energy to float downward one
beautiful brushstroke after the other
the whole body is brushed upward and
downward breathe in brushstroke comes up
you breathe down brushstroke goes down
you might find your body just slightly
rocking a little bit in concert with the
inhalation and the exhalation
and throughout you'll just feel the
energy flowing upward and downward
you
and now since that the energy is coming
just out of your body
the front and back into the body so that
it begins to seem as if the skin is
permeable
the inn
brings energy just outside the body the
exhalation brings the body into the pot
I'm sorry brings the energy into the
body exhalation energy goes out
inhalation energy comes in it might also
feel a little bit like a rocking
experience or like a brush stroke back
and forth back and forth in and out and
so on
you
and now imagine or feel or sense that
the energy from within you is being
carried farther and farther away from
you that is that the energy is expanding
into the space nearby
and then is going farther than the space
nearby to the farthest possible
conceivable or imaginable space and
therefore the energy is doing nothing
but expanding beyond the bounds of the
skin as far as the mind can imagine or
conceive of
it is nothing but expansion
you
throughout this meditation for many of
us there has been a witness or an
observer or an aware or the one that
seems to be doing all this therefore we
can now install energy in via wearer or
the observer or the witness the one
that's been as it were standing behind
all of this
therefore install energy in the aware or
in you so that you are nothing but
energy in fact do not install energy in
the aware rather be the energy itself
anytime some
tries to stand back from the process of
installation see that you too cannot
stand back from being installed with C
fused with and therefore entirely filled
up with energy
you
therefore energy is everywhere and
perhaps it could also be said know where
in particular therefore there is no
inside or outside
no above or below
no forward or backward
everything is energy
and if
there is no thing
rather all processes are energetic
everything is vibrating
everything which is no thing in
particular because no substance in
particular is is just vibrating
pulsating energy
you
and now ask yourself a question
and allow that question to fill you all
up with the sense of mystery do not try
to answer the question intellectually
just ask the question and see where it
takes you
ask yourself the question Who am I
ask yourself Who am I
Who am I
you
ask yourself where am I
am i here
could I be there
is there any sense to be made of here or
there
am i in space at all
you
ask yourself the question when am I
MIB for
could I be after
can I make any sense
of talk of before or after or am I only
ever always now
ask yourself what am i what what am I
but even that is too much because it
assumes that there's a what different
from and separate from I
so ask yourself am i I
em aye aye
you
but even that is saying too much
therefore ask yourself simply
mysteriously
I
you
but even that is
just too much
therefore sink
and rest
sink and rest
in the nameless
you
and now if you have your eyes closed
slowly open your eyes but while you do
so try to don't even try to allow
yourself to maintain this place 'less
place that we came to that has
maintained this place 'less place even
when your eyes are open even when your
senses are open and available to the
external world
you
and
yourself in a comfortable position and
take your time you can put your glasses
back on if you've taken them off
and you can slowly turn your video
cameras back home
you
okay I think most of
have our cameras back on and so let's
come to the we space meditative
discourse at a we skate we space
discursive meditation or part two and
here let me just suggest that the place
we found if I may you give a name to it
for the moment could be called the heart
I'm just using that provisionally if
you're not inclined to that term then
you can just let it go but the point of
the second part then is to be able to
speak from this place if you feel
stirred to speak if you feel no stirring
to speak then you can just keep sinking
into this particular place 'less place
this kind of silence the silence before
speech and if you feel that anything is
bothering you there's any kind of
resistance then take that as your point
of departure just ask yourself what is
it that is that which I'm resisting and
you can go into that
and if you find that the resistance
dissolves then you can come back to the
conversation we're having together this
is not meant to be a question-and-answer
session
so I don't see myself any longer it's
playing the role of the one who's
speaking throughout the course of this
part nor do I see myself as expert
answering questions
I'm simply interested in seeing what
emerges in and through this particular
genre
okay so I'm going to mute myself and if
anyone feels some kind of stirring to
speak please do so
you
what I'm struck by is the resonance that
you generated and communicated in taking
us through that you know I'm very
grateful for that experience I think
in a deep way in a deep way it's an
appropriate and beautiful way to open
this portal what it brought to mind or
cause to be presents most now is how
that kind of state is at once a settling
there's also this latent sort of
potentiality that that's that's right
there and could be just expanded
you know breathed out at any moment
I think the quietness before speech
seems to be a really beautiful dynamic
there yeah it's the lessening and then
out again so yeah I appreciate the
I appreciate that dynamic here I mean
I'm very interested in where this is
where this is opening into
talking I just felt awards viously just
just enjoyed your energy Tim I'm sending
you appreciation and love and what came
to mind when you were talking is that
there's a sense when I was doing that
meditation where I just felt transparent
and visible see-through but at the same
time completely here like more here than
I normally a.m.
I am I felt this strong sense when he
asked where are you and who are you that
they were almost the same thing in that
kind of found that those is energy that
we kind of only are energy and that sort
of interacts with the world and in a
weird way if she sort of close your eyes
and imagine where the energy is that's
also who you are it's a bit hard to
explain but I got a strong sense of that
you
there are a couple moments that really
struck me I can only remember a few of
them one of them was when you asked can
I be anywhere other than now it's kind
of trivial when you think about it but
it really hit me at the right time and
I'm wondering what the experience is
like for you kind of pulling people to
the edge of their definition of
themselves what does that experience
like is it finally caution us against
not against not really caution us
against but you kind of remind us that
there will be resistances and I think
that's helpful but I'm wondering what
it's like for you to be the one who's
pulling
you
and
I I just closed my eyes and let things
happen
[Laughter]
that's it man
and just feeling what's happening and I
think it's
and I guess I'm just seeing whether
people are willing to go along
[Music]
and set aside
yes sir
understanding according to the logos
according to you or ordinary rationality
and whether they will melt into what's
happening so it's it's entirely in the
vein I hope of an invitation
[Music]
I think this notion of invitation is
really interesting something you did
which enabled a really beautiful
continuity was in beginning the guidance
you said that if there is something
you're not
Celine these aren't the words you use
but if there was sort of a snag you hid
right if you weren't able to attend
precisely to what was being invited to
to pay attention to that resistance and
so what I'm interested in is both its
how to extend the hand how to invite to
do so in a way that still enables
absolute elegance in the knotek's if
someone's not accepting you know as I
can offer it's okay not to accept off we
go it's like to still be in touch with
like the full scope of possible
resonance even when that is not a direct
kind of yes let's go together right now
I think that dynamic the dynamic to do
with invitation and acceptance and the
landscape which enables the not
accepting of an invitation to ultimately
support both the accepting and they're
not accepting
I want to say that for me I'm finding it
a whole ton easier to not have my mind
running wild in the silence between
people's words I think I'm really really
resonating strongly with Tim's original
message his first comment about the
beauty of the dynamic between the
silence and the words and I'm hearing
the silence and I'm noticing my comfort
and appreciation for it and it's
allowing me a different kind of
attendance to what people are saying and
I'm noticing that in myself and
appreciating it and really loving my
participation in the conversation and
just hearing the things and the silence
together bringing me a lot of joy
you
I'm kind of appreciating that this is
usually something that I sort of do by
myself
or in person with people but to have
this level of connection without being
in the same place I think is very
special it's very new to me yeah I'm
very grateful to be involved in and
something like this
you
something came up when Tim was talking
about the invitation and how I hold dad
is that when you're throwing out that
invitation there's sort of or at least
when I'm doing it right or it feels like
I'm doing it right there's a sense of a
radical availability to the other person
and I think I'm great
creating a greater sensitivity to who
can accept that invitation and and and
welcome my availability and then I also
have a sensitivity who can't so there's
sort of like a spectrum and the ones who
can't there's a sense of like I almost
hurt or annoyance or subtle anger but I
like with Tim was saying is that or how
I how I read that it's like that itself
is sort of an art form to maintain that
invitation that had that availability of
available that stayed available I should
say when the other person can't receive
it or it's not ready to receive it
you
what it brings to mind Peter and I I
like how you put that what it brings to
mind is maybe we can take a relationship
with a relative I can consider certain
experiences of my life the people that
have a loving relationship with that as
paned of a sense in which there's
something that they're let's say they're
rejecting about me and it hurts and
there's a sense of of holding the
boundary of that as in this rejection is
real there's something here that is not
being seen and accepted and that is that
is part of this relationship that is
that is a dynamic that that that is
painful to both of us yet at the same
time work through that looking into the
eyes there's there's something behind it
there's that there's a deeper love it's
not connected somehow
maybe there's some egoic block or
however we might want to however we
might want to put that as something
compromised in the map it's like no I'm
holding on to my map of this you know
and there's pain there but then there's
a deeper sense of actually in the end
really we're still in this together and
so to hold to that and to presence that
has that state of nothingness in the
here and now of this ripe potentiality
lasts on how we are still involved in
and there's a deep sense of caring
somehow in that that's that's beyond
what might be paid even on a deep level
but still nevertheless not the whole
picture
just deep maps and incongruencies but
that looking into the eye there's that
love there far back into the iron as a
truss
that over time as we move on as that
particular invitation hasn't been
accepted that actually we are still in
some sense connected
yeah
my Tim I resonated a a lot with what you
just said it feels to me like the
conforms appear out of emptiness there's
places where different forms will be
connected to each other in places they
won't and it sounds so simple when I put
it that way but of course if we were the
forms and we're emotional beings and we
have these momentous experiences and
mentis desires really that you didn't
even expect and they they get denied to
us in ways we didn't expect and can't
make and can't comprehend and don't have
the tools to comprehend it can it can
send us you can send us in places that
are that we need to explore in order to
in order to learn more we put it there I
feel like I would not not to not to get
away from this on this here and now too
much but I feel like there's elements
there they would love to see out there
sometimes when people are are feeling
these kinds of pains
could you expand on that a little bit
more what kinds of pains and what would
you like to see uh when I mean one this
is just one one expression of it perhaps
but when there's when there's groups and
they feel unity and there's a there's
just a place for that people want to go
and others don't but there's a definite
rejection of the police aspects of it
aspects that feel they feel essential
right it's sacred or without the word
those words necessarily units felt of
course and how and how much that can
cause and it can cause a lot of pain and
people can respond without really
understanding the experience I'm not
gonna need too many unfortunate things
and that helps
I feel like I'm I am resonating with
both Tim and milk said that I'm also
kind of thinking about it in terms of
themself as far as when I was going
through process I found that certain
aspects of my automatic harvest didn't
want to do it like my draw my shoulders
were like to pronounce specs of my
consciousness and psyche we're also like
this right now I'm thinking of things
earlier the day like there were they
there were these blocks that were me for
sure and it is kind of like the blocks
that we have with other people in
connections are also locks and we have
within ourselves there I realized
through come up automatically and just
different persistent thoughts and
different resistance I don't know that
that's kind of what this is with the
idea of the resistance of because er
it's also the resistance of the other
weapons
I thought that was really beautiful
you
perhaps putting these perspectives
together what comes to mind is this up
it's a clash of what is felt to be
sacred within as it comes into contact
with what is held as sacred without from
an external source and both involved and
then the sacredness something trauma
vague he talks about distinction to the
sacred the sacredness of the process
where we might be with each other
fundamentally you know reciprocally
opening way in a manner that can
transform
[Music]
what has been held as sacred to really
imagine it revivify as a symbol as an
icon as a relationship or the kind of an
understanding and identity a renewal of
that sense yeah
I just want to present something just
point something out when amy was talking
about her shoulders kind of tensing up
and resisting hi I could relate to that
a lot I could almost feel my spine kind
of shaking a bit before his try to say
something and then I notice Tim how
eloquently he uses his kind of embodied
language and it seems so like fluent and
it obviously seems to help you if I'm
right if I'm right Tim and wondering if
the relationship with your body has a
Ford to you presence for other people
yeah that's really interesting it is
something I'm conscious of I
you know in many different settings I
actually like to go out to different
places in the city or in nature but
often cultural kind of places and I like
to dance with my headphones and it's
interesting because you know anyone
could go out there and move around but
if you move in a way that is somehow
pained or discordance it's going to be
very unsettling and it's been
interesting to watch when people feel
relaxed around me in a space and often
when I'm moving feels very similar to
thinking and so it seems to be quite
remarkable that how we hold ourselves
is enabling of safety and again an
invitation to participate and ultimately
be winners and transform the not knowing
[Music]
a certain state of vulnerability that's
nevertheless connected somehow with you
know some sort of elegance and a desire
ultimately to be helpful you know to
offer something to the space and you
know you see and we could go to a club
or a bar or something someone comes
along and bring some real life with
their movement it just lifts everything
you know someone just comes in and
people are willing for that to happen
and there's a way people can open this
space like that and it's some there
seems to be a deep continuity there in
what we pick up on and so
I find that drop experientially the
state is quite similar yeah
you
I was just wondering if anyone has
experienced where your heart or your
mind wants to connect but you feel
physical resistance like for example
during that meditation and actually just
during life in general I find that my
heart always yearned to be closer to
people and to you know feel more
connected but physically I feel stuck
and I'm not sure if that's something
that comes from you know deep inside or
maybe past trauma yeah I was just
wondering what you know whether other
people have experienced that sort of
push and pull of like you wanna be close
and connected but you know something's
holding you back yeah I am I feel like
quite a lot taraf it's really a strange
experience because on one hand you
actually know deep down that you really
care about the person all the people or
whatever it is I I personally get this
thing right even though I feel that I'm
still incapable of articulating things
that I know the other person needs to
hear and then I probably should say
follow the relationship as a whole but
there's like as you say that was like
this weird physical like wall that kind
of filters things through and I I've
almost also thought that I'm kind of
like the other person feels like that so
it's nice to know that somebody else
shares that same kind of thing I thought
I was going crazy
I'm curious to know you know how maybe
other people have addressed that or I
mean I really it kind of comes down to
you know letting your your your wall
down or your protection yeah any
thoughts on how other people have been
able to do that
I can only speak from personal
experience and I'm by from when a means
an expert in that but I would say like
any of these things that come up for us
I think the first step is being aware of
it when it happens and once you sort of
captured that awareness I I sort of
delve into if possible like if you're
not in a situation where you can't tell
into it in a sort of meditative practice
it almost asked the question well where
is where is this coming from
us and I find that sometimes can help to
identify the cause of over what might be
the rate where it's originating from I
don't always get an answer to that
question but I think I think it's a
useful sort of pathway to take in those
remnants this year as you sort of said
you kind of know what you need to do but
for some reason you can't and I think
it's something it's useful to so delve
into why why they tweaked on I'd like to
get in on that question I mean I think I
could not relate more directly to the
question of do you feel physical
resistance in your body and I think that
the first I would connect us back to
another question from the meditation
where we were being asked to consider
what we are and the meditation really
wisely asks you to notice that what you
are is not separate from what you're
experiencing and I would connect that to
this question by saying that when I feel
that resistance I often have I want to
locate that resistance external to
myself I want
make it about whether or not the other
person is right or and you know like and
whatever sense of right like are they
logically correct are they factually
correct are they whatever but to make it
some kind of intellectual game I feel
this way because someone else is wrong
in some way or maybe it's connected to
some trauma that I have it's bringing up
you know something from my own past and
sentimental relationships or or whatever
that is and I don't notice that that
feeling comes from within me I feel like
it must be something about the universe
or the other person that's causing this
in me but when I stop to meditate like
what what is this what is this feeling
that I'm having I noticed that it's not
external to me that it's inside of me
I want to add that I have a similar
experience quite often of recognizing
that it's internal to me I've developed
a little bit of a pragmatic habit for
dealing with situations like that I sort
of used a mnemonic to remind myself of a
state of clarity and I use it when I
don't have the time to actually dive
into my emotions but there's something
interesting that I want to mention about
that demen demonic is just a really
quick motion where I tapped the center
of our head and it just sort of clears
clears my mental space and I immediately
feel lighter I immediately feel easier
and it just allows me to be more present
in the moment because it basically like
hard wipes whatever was on my mind that
was taking up so much space and I'm you
know cluttering up the fluidity of my
present like cluttering cluttering me up
but I think it's I take it one really
interesting thing about these
experiences is that I noticed that I
don't always use it and I think that I
use it far more often in situations
where I notice that there's something
important to the other person in a
conversation and that I notice when when
I attend to the fact that there's more
to the other person and I notice that
this is a personal relationship and we
have a dynamic that we're developing and
there's something important to them then
i'ma mind it that I can wipe away
whatever's stopping me from being able
to engage meaningfully with the other
person but it's odd that I don't do this
so often when I don't attend when I
don't notice that there's something
important to the other person and I
think that's interesting I think it sort
of speaks to that idea that this has to
be something that's internal to me
that's it's clunking up the conversation
the ability to engage with the other
person meaningfully
the roar also speaks to the idea that
the awareness that Tristan mentioned
that the awareness of this comes first
it's there's something that needs to be
there some awareness in order for us to
be able to meaningfully pull out a
behavior like that and meaningfully try
to reframe and engage choose to engage
more deeply more president Li I'm
curious if you in those moments have
ever actually got to a point where you
were aware of it but you still felt felt
that there was this block and you still
decided to to not say or do the thing
even though you're very salient of what
it wasn't needed to be done
hmm it's a good question
I think it's I say that cuz I've
experienced it quite a lot
hmm the idea of becoming aware of a
block but not being able to move it
I think I think there's a caveat I
should add that I probably have only
done this in situations where I was
aware somehow somewhere some part of me
was aware would needed to be done
whether whether that was just holding
space in being curious which it often is
so I felt like because because I've had
more awareness of what should be done
once I've chosen to engage that way I
don't have a lot of moments like that
but I but I have had plenty of moments
where for whatever reason I haven't sort
of reconnected with that part of myself
that's there and can listen and can be
there and and I've often had that where
I noticed there's a problem but I don't
throw up the mnemonic and and then I the
problem just kind of sticks around and
and then my rational mind gets really
really all up in it and says I'm just
gonna solve this problem pragmatically
here's a here's the function that will
speed up our conversation and get us to
the point where we want to be less
comfortable
I always feel uncomfortable when that
happens
I don't feel happy about myself about
that either I've questioned my friend
pointed out to me that I would always
look at my hand
all right and then I realized I was
doing the same thing that that he said
you did when you and he tapped your head
it's almost like I was reminding myself
that I can take a third-person view of
what I'm doing and I was doing it
unconsciously so I I'm wondering if but
but then when I realized that I was
doing it when did you realize that this
was a thing and and afterwards did you
did that change your use of it or like
did you ever do it unconsciously and not
realized for a time and then realized it
and then used it differently
ah so Kelly before I answer I want to
say that I heard a lot of really loud
audio from your side and I'm not sure if
there's something that you can tweak
about that but there was some really
loud sounds that came from your side if
there's something you can do about them
but to answer a question no there were
other things that I've done
subconsciously sort of without being
aware of it but this particular thing it
came from the idea fundamentally that we
can grow as people and we can become
better human beings and that I've had a
few experiences that were really
motivating and eye-opening that said I
could do better and I can have better
relationships and I can live a more
meaningful present life and then I and
then I developed this and I said okay
well how am I going to do this I need I
need a mnemonic and then I trained it
and I sat at home and I went okay this
is the mindset these are the theme
feelings these are the emotions this is
the awareness it must connect here and I
just repeated that a couple of times and
felt it and visualized it and then I
practiced it in easier settings I
practiced it where I thought it wasn't
so hard to activate that part of myself
where I was already sort of vaguely
aware that yeah I could pull that that
mode of me in and then once I practiced
it it became easier then I was and then
I started being able to do it in other
situations for me yeah it doesn't have
that that's that's pretty cool I think
one of the other things I'm just
realizing a few DISA said that you Lee
was there like different intensities of
it as well and I found that um now that
I'm looking back on it it sort of
depends on the environment and the
activity that I was in that that some
things actually generate that kind of
response and for me personally it's it's
whenever I'm working on computers and in
technology
or doing anything where I'm super
conscious and using using the prefrontal
cortexes pros a lot in regards to
solving some kind of intellectual
problem I'm less likely to engage on
that emotional side of things it's
almost like those walls come up and and
the more I go into that sort of
conscious analytical side of things the
the thicker that will get which is kind
of a problem because I work as a
programmer so I'm in that space a lot
and it's actually caused a lot of
problems for myself for my wife and yeah
it's just kind of interesting to
recognize when these things happen and
what is it that there are actually
certain activities and I think what's
interesting is that by by being aware of
what actually triggers it in the first
place it might actually help you to go
into that activity without awareness
that hey if somebody does come and
interact with me I need to be super
cognizant of super salient of that this
is a problem usually when when I partake
in this kind of kind of thing
I'm sorry good Oh
I was gonna ask a question - I was
reminded of Tara's original question
while Tristan was speaking and I became
curious to know if the awareness of that
wall looks different for different
people like maybe I can imagine it would
take different form in in our bodies but
I wonder if there are other things like
maybe it's certainly for me it's not
always physical I might feel it
physically because of tension but I sort
of almost like for me that tension feels
like it's self created and the real wall
is mental it's abstract it's a set of
thoughts that are taking up mental space
and I wonder if there are different
types of feelings people have felt when
they feel something like that wall
because I I don't know if yeah I would
imagine that the experiences are
different and probably the solutions
have to be different than and I'm super
curious to see what other people's
awareness of this kind of sensation has
been like what's coming up for me and
this is sort of a device that I I'm
developing I return to and Terra comes
to mind because I know she's plugged
into the stoic community and this is
sort of like a stoic algorithm that I
run anytime my serenity gets disrupted
or disturbed and it's sort of like this
default frame that every single emotion
or felt sense that I experience is sort
of like a friend giving me advice and
sometimes that friend is not always
giving me the best advice Ric sometimes
friends don't always give the best
advice but they mean well and so when I
feel an emotion that's intense that
throws me out of the the moment or the
here and now I just give I say thank you
you know I said like thank you friend
for for giving me this advice right now
and that sort of just that alone just
sort of kind of like calms calms it down
a bit and then maybe I can return to it
and and sort of do some work in her work
on it but by doing this you kind of like
I got a sensitivity to the like I guess
the ecology of felt senses that are
operating in my body and and having a
relationship with each one of them and
then building a sensitivity when when
they get triggered when they return and
just building a relationship with that
friend that device that that emotion
that that felt sense and I think by
doing that in my own body my own
awareness I feel it and other people
more when when those felt senses become
activated in them and I think it's
helping me become a more of intuitive
person so just just the right thing to
say at the right time becomes more clear
when when I'm with someone who is also
in a state where their their serenity is
disrupted
sounds to me like Peter you there it's a
movement of creating and re-establishing
a we space rather than an ask them of
somehow some trigger point being
challenged some opens it back up again
to really being with and ultimately yeah
collaborating it's a nice yeah I like
that sort of um it's like finding your
way back to communitas and one thing
like just an example like right now when
I noticed when people were asking
questions like direct questions
annoyance was coming up in my body and
like no don't ask questions because I
have like a story that like if we want a
midwife a community oz asking question
creates a different energy it's like and
I'm more analytical more and we're more
in your head and it's less from your
heart and I don't know if this is
necessarily the case but this is the
story and so when I was the feeling this
annoyance come up in my body I just said
you know thank you
and then sort of just went away a bit
one thing that I've been learning about
myself is that all these talks of all
this talk rather of walls and and and
blocks and resistances I think I used to
understand in terms of not being whole
or not being perfect somehow and
therefore it was very easy I think to
get involved in some form of spiritual
bypass as it's called or just to sweep
sweep them away
and then I think the inclination is to
believe that walls or resistances or
whatever our problems and therefore as
problems they need to be gotten rid of
and that took me a little while to see
that that may not be the correct
understanding of what they are instead
the philosophical side of me is just
learning to extend the inquiry in a
different way so philosophy is the love
the loving pursuit of truth then I'm
wondering about how any kind of
resistance I have is actually know I'm
speaking in mystical terms but as a
pointer it's a pointer to what someone
call the nameless absolute the upon
Ishod suggests that every every form in
name is actually a pointer or a longing
for the absolute so another way of
putting all this is that when I sense
some kind of resistance I have whatever
it is I can I can say thank you as Peter
did and and then I can see where it's
carrying me what kind of truth and
pretty broad sense is trying to disclose
as a consequence I'm not thinking that
this is a problem anymore
it's what Buddhists call a Dharma door
or a gateless gate and that has made it
it's partly conceptual but it's also
partly meditative or contemplatively
shifted my willingness to to really love
the truth as it arises in my ordinary
experience and to see what is behind or
beneath or both what's presenting itself
to me once more
Mystikal weaning
you
I actually really resonated with one
point that you made about sort of
feeling like the resistance maybe came
from like something you didn't you know
you didn't feel like you were perfect or
maybe not good enough I I was kind of
pondering on the idea that I feel like
for me especially my resistance I think
comes from a place of feeling different
than other people and I think generally
a lot of people that are more
intellectual or deep thinkers are often
or maybe often do feel different and
maybe feel like a bit left out but just
kind of like I don't know if you guys
are like me but sometimes you feel like
you're kind of on the outside looking in
you know yeah and like I also have like
a physical disability so I feel like in
that sense I've always felt a bit
different than people and I think
sometimes my resistance comes from just
yeah not feeling like I mean similar to
other people you know anyways I just
thought I'd throw that out there for
discussion
I think that when you have these kind of
feelings of being different if you need
to kind of hide within the select tool
and kind of make that the safe space for
yourself versus where they stuff that I
do the general and it's been very sweet
I was thinking about this idea of loving
the wall versus hating it or wanting it
to change or to be different sort of
seen what happens when you actually like
those those things that you do to create
or maintain that's been trying to like
it off of them before they're ready to
you
I think perhaps perhaps I can synthesize
a little bit and speak to both of these
points particularly yours sorrow can
definitely feel like the case when there
is much on your mind to express or that
the particular wool you're experiencing
is the kind of wool that if you were to
express it would all of you would all of
a sudden be quite substantial for the
people around you to deal with right
you'd be putting yourself in the fore in
a way that might be like the way it's
almost could be rocking the boat or
taking too much time in the space you
know but nevertheless for you to sort of
authentically presents that it feels
like such a big thing so it's like these
blocks that we experience especially in
relationships just how deep do they go
just what may be unsettled and that is
well as a deep as a deep deep challenge
this is something about presencing that
though requires is going to require of
the container that it can hold that
presencing right that there's an
adaptability there it requires a sort of
cooperation and necessarily as well as
sort of requires you to just extend
beyond your boundary in a way that's
putting yourself in the light light so
to speak in a way that well it might it
might it might not work out in the short
time it might not might fall flat in a
way you know part of a part of a process
you know and I think stronger for it but
it's a challenge it's a challenge
there's more to say that but I think
that's yeah I feel that
[Music]
I take a risk and try to state something
from public transportation that I wanted
to jump in on the idea that we
experience these things in our mind and
not in our bodies which is a useful way
to think about that sometimes but also
it can be useful to switch over to the
idea that this to be the framework that
there's no distinction between mind and
body that maybe there's a spectrum of
places that you feel things and some
things are more mental than others but
to draw a line between I'm feeling this
block in my mind but not in my body
sometimes dissolving that mind-body
connection can help you to place the
block more clearly and and be able to
deal with it a little bit more directly
yeah not almost reminds me of kind of a
pasta for those who are familiar with
that kind of mentality which is
everything is kind of reflected somehow
in our bodies and they kind of had this
idea that by not sort of observing these
things it creates this sort of spiral
that sort of spirals out of control
because we're not aware of it and that
sort of reflection in our bodies then
that sort of creates an unconscious
reflection in our mind which creates
more of a sensation in the body which
then sort of creates that spiral and one
of the things about this sort of style
of meditation which is really
interesting is that just by simply
observing it not doing anything or
changing anything just simply just
observing it you you break that
automatic spiral and it's kind of this
whole idea of recognizing whether it's
mental or physical this thing would be
it positive or negative
and just they sort of have this phrase
accept the reality as it is not as you'd
like it to be but but as it is and
remain economist and I think I don't
know I think that I think that might be
a potential way to look into these roles
and and to deepen their the the link
between the mind and the body which is
so apparent
um absolutely instability pasta and
another type of meditation which both of
which have helped with these kinds of
things but the other kind the other an
aspect of the other kind that may be
pertinent is to observe thing and to see
like an experiential and experiential
thing and see some space between the
stimulus and response or between like
various various experiences one that
fall after another
seeing that space can be you know what
these almost like giving you the idea
that the second thing need not follow
from the first necessarily although it's
not that it's not that wordy of course
sometimes the terms the spaciousness are
invoked here
I'm probably biased and I think and
biased on the point about to make and I
think Tim Taylor and Andrew and a few
others here share this bias is that the
key to a lot of this is like being good
at having conversations and dialogue and
being in relationship and there's just
exercise that I like that guy Journal
every morning and there's exercise I do
sometimes think it came from Jung called
active imagination where you just sort
of like map words you translate what
your felt senses are saying into words
so if you feel fear you might just say
run away if you feel anger you know just
as a tack or whatever it wants to
communicate it's like wind I hear people
saying the wall a few times like what is
the wall saying if you translate that to
propositions or English What's it
telling you and and I think maybe that
the first step to being in good
relationship with that felt sense that
real thing that's existing inside you is
that start having good conversations
with it and then once you start having
good conversations with it then you know
and maybe a good relationship conform
with it
I really appreciate what you just said
there something just clicked for dead
nice your money yeah I think that idea
of like if you if you were to describe
the wall what would it be
that's like a really interesting concept
because I think the more you sort of
delve into it and the more you break it
apart the more you realize the wall
isn't really kind of there it's just
these things we think are there but yeah
that's a really cool exercise
I really resonated with the advice to
start communicating directly with all
sorts of different things that could
come up and trying to translate them
I've never thought of trying to
translate them I've always been I guess
afraid that if I miss translate them
I'll be building in sort of poor habits
or poor responses but I I really
appreciate this because you're right
it's it's not I have to start the
conversation somewhere and and
practicing that conversation in a
comfortable space that's my own like a
journal seems like a really good way of
doing that
so I'd really appreciate that it seems
to work for how I've been thinking about
this
and I'll try it and see how Cass
I went to a therapist who started having
me do that kind of work by trying to
locate where in the body you feel the
resistance and you would often start
roughly with like the gut the heart or
the head and there's a lot of different
personality constructs that use those
three centers and not just personality
constructs but you know lots of ancient
wisdom that uses those three centers as
being focuses of different ways of being
and that was really helpful as a tool
for me to to conjure where in my body I
felt it and then try to imagine a
scenario that would pull that resistance
back up for me and try to seal how it
begins
I would arise and how it goes away all
of that is very useful as something that
can be noticed for me
maybe we should talk to the point that
Taylor made as well which I kind of like
which is what is the world's purpose and
how does or did it serve me I'm just
reading that up just so we can address
that whispers
hi so I just want to say something since
we're talking about how to get rid of
the wall or whatever to address it what
helps me and the meditation itself is
helpful in that aspect it's kind of to
get out of your body and to look at this
as some kind of a brain imperfection or
something like that and to realize oh I
just have this brain or whatever you
believe in some kind of feelings that I
might be feeling and maybe I don't want
to feel them but that's okay because
everybody is imperfect I am a part of
this huge universe I don't even know if
the past or the future exists and so on
and so forth just to get out of your
body and to kind of look at yourself
from a third-person perspective that
that helps me now we can go on to the
questions it's just one I wanted to say
that
how how do you approach that Ivan how do
you approach that idea of taking
yourself out into the third-person G is
like a an exercise you want for yourself
well this I've done this kind of
meditation before so it's that's that
helps to kind of I don't know to think
of yourself as I don't know it goes it
goes in the direction of it doesn't
really matter at this particular point
in time we're all imperfect we're all
gonna die we're all just nobodies in
this huge universe and just realizing
that kind of helps me but when you
actually do the meditation you kind of
feel it at the same time whew so you
kind of feel yourself at ease and then
I'm able to analyze it more for me the
other thing that helps is to actually
try to understand where it's coming from
well the where the wall is coming from
and when I do that then I have a choice
about how how I want to proceed and that
kind of helps me
thank you very much everyone we have
about 10 minutes or so remaining give or
take and I'd like to take us through one
final meditation together and so it
might be a good idea to turn off your
cameras again if you'd like to do that
and make sure you're on mute and again
you can put yourself in a comfortable
position perhaps you want to take your
your glasses off if you're wearing them
if you don't want to take part in
meditation that's fine too we can go
back to the the theme of today's
conversation which has been resistance
or specifically walls and indeed it
there's at any point in the meditation
when you feel some kind of resistance or
block or a wall you've listened to all
the lovely things and important things
that people have said today so you might
avail yourself of one of those
approaches or perhaps multiple
approaches okay you can have your eyes
open or closed it might be easier if you
have your eyes closed at least easier
for many of us and and
we'll start with the feet and I will
invite you to install light in your feet
therefore your feet the right foot first
URL
left foot next is just light
you can imagine that or you can
visualize that or you can sense that or
you can feel that it's not important
that there is some profound light in
your feet just that there's some
intention directed toward the feet and
the installation of light there and then
you can take your right leg and
all light all the way up your right leg
to your calf the knee the thigh
with the result that your right leg is
entirely light
emanating
brilliant light
likewise you can install energy in your
left leg
with the result that your left leg is
just brilliant emanating light
and now bring your
attention to your genitals and your butt
that area to be entirely filled up
with light
and now come to the trunk
it's
they install energy all the way
throughout your trunk
throughout the front throughout the back
and between the front and the back
so that the entire middle of the body is
luminous light
come down to the left hand and the left
arm
[Music]
install energy all the way through your
left hand and all the way up your left
arm
[Music]
all the way up to this shoulder
and now you can imagine or visualize or
sense or feel that the left arm is
completely filled with light
is nothing other than
nothing separate from light
you
likewise you can install energy and your
right arm starting with the right hand
going up and through the right hand up
and through the forearm up and through
the upper arm all the way to the right
shoulder
not only
sigh but also within
one sees or feels or experiences
light
and now come to the neck
you can install energy
way around all the way in all the way
through the neck so that the neck is
just
print
with light
and now come to the head
you can install light
all the way throughout the head
from the back
up the front through the middle to the
crown and perhaps even slightly above
the crown beyond the crown
as a result the Indy head is entirely
filled with permeated by saturated with
and utterly alive with light
you
from the tips of the toes from the heels
all the way up through and around the
body
up
to the head and up beyond the crown of
the head
there is nothing but
brilliant
light
you
consider the possibility that you
yourself are only
utterly completely light
you
it is not
you you feel the light rather it is that
you are the light
it is not that you see
the light
instead you are
[Music]
the light
you
consider the very possibility that the
light what you are is also love
you
plentiful generative generous capacious
over flowing love
you
and now we can open our eyes and as or
opening our eyes
let us live the possibility that
light is loving
and when you're ready you can turn on
the cameras your cameras rather
you
thank you very much everyone Thank You
Reggie
welcome Peter thank you everyone it was
nothing to share this time with you
forward seeing you all again nice
meeting you and you PA see bye-bye
everyone
thank you okay everyone you guys